

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Data Science Group, Institute for Basic Science (IBS), Daejeon 34126, Korea

■ (+82) 10-8845-2205 | kdkyum531@gmail.com | kdkyum.github.io | kdkyum | kdkyum | kdkyum | kdkyum531 | Google Scholar

Summary_

I am a physicist passionate about AI and did my PhD in physics at KAIST, Korea. Under professor Hawoong Jeong's supervision, I worked on applications of ML in complex systems and statistical physics. My current research focus is understanding highly complex nonequilibrium systems, such as biological systems, active matter, and others in nature, through stochastic thermodynamics with ML-based approaches.

Education

Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST)

Daejeon, Korea

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (PHD) IN PHYSICS, ADVISOR: PROF. HAWOONG JEONG

Mar. 2016 - Feb. 2022

• Dissertation: Nonequilibrium Statistical Physics Study using Deep Learning

Seoul National University (SNU)

Seoul, Korea

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (BS) IN PHYSICS WITH A MINOR IN COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

2011 - 2015

Experience

Institute for Basic Science (IBS)

Daejeon, Korea Mar. 2022 - present

SENIOR RESEARCHER

- Hosted by prof. Meeyoung Cha (Chief Investigator).
- Data Science Group, Center for Mathematical and Computational Sciences.

G. Kim, **D.-K. Kim** & H. Jeong, *bioRxiv* 2021.10.27.466049, *kgspiano/Music* (Under Review)

Samsung Electronics

Hwaseong, Korea

MACHINE LEARNING INTERN

Sep. 2017 - Dec. 2017

- Collaborated with Daniel Kim, PhD (Senior Data Scientist).
- Improved anomaly image classification tasks via distributed multi-GPU training methods of Keras & Spark.
- Implemented a distributed image searching framework to detect similar patterns in images through Elasticsearch.

Publication

Transformer as a hippocampal memory consolidation model based on NMDAR-inspired nonlinearity DK. Kim, J. Kwon, M. Cha, & C. J. Lee, Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)	2023
SUBTLE: An unsupervised platform with temporal link embedding that maps animal behavior J. Kwon, S. Kim, DK. Kim, J. Joo, S. H. Kim, M. Cha, & C. J. Lee, <i>bioRxiv</i> 2023.04.12.536531 (Under Review)	2023
Multidimensional entropic bound: Estimator of entropy production for Langevin dynamics with an arbitrary	
time-dependent protocol S. Lee, DK. Kim, J. M. Park, W. K. Kim, H. Park & J. S. Lee, <i>Phys. Rev. Research</i> 5, 013194	2023
Neural Classification of Terrestrial Biomes V. Shen, DK, KIM, E. Zeller, M. Cha, <i>IEEE International Conference on Big Data and Smart Computing (BigComp)</i>	2023
Transformer needs NMDA receptor nonlinearity for long-term memory DK, KIM, J. KWON, M. CHA, C. J. LEE, NeurIPS-W 2022 (Memory in Artificial and Real Intelligence)	2022
Inferring dissipation maps from videos using convolutional neural networks	
Y. Bae, DK. Kim & H. Jeong, <i>Phys. Rev. Research</i> 4, 033094, <i>qodudrud/CNEEP</i>	2022
Estimating entropy production with odd-parity state variables via machine learning DK. KIM, S. LEE & H. JEONG, <i>Phys. Rev. Research</i> 4, 023051, Adkyum/odd_neep	2022
Spontaneous emergence of music detectors in a deep neural network	

2021

Deep reinforcement learning for feedback control in a collective flashing ratchet

D.-K. KIM & H. JEONG, Phys. Rev. Research 3, L022002, 🗘 kdkyum/RatchetDRL

2021

Learning Entropy Production via Neural Networks

D.-K. KIM, Y. BAE, S. LEE & H. JEONG, Phys. Rev. Lett. 125, 140604, Adkyum/neep

2020

Multi-Label Classification of Historical Documents by Using Hierarchical Attention Networks

D.-K. KIM, B. LEE, D. KIM & H. JEONG, J. Korean Phys. Soc. 76, 368

2020

Skills.

Programming Languages Python*, R, JAVA, Scheme, C, C++ (* skills daily used)

ML Frameworks JAX*, PyTorch*, Keras, TensorFlow **Distributed Computing** Slurm*, Spark, Elasticsearch

Award.

2021.8.30 Pre-doctoral Fellow of Physics at KAIST

Daejeon, Korea

Presentation

Working and reference memory in transformers on a navigation task

2022 KIAS CAINS SUMMER WORKSHOP (INVITED TALK)

Sono Belle, Jeju, Korea

Sep. 2, 2022

Deep reinforcement learning for optimal mechanism in active Brownian particles

2022 NONEQUILIBRIUM STATISTICAL PHYSICS OF COMPLEX SYSTEMS (CONFERENCE, POSTER)

KIAS, Seoul, Korea Jul. 25, 2022

Exploring optimal mechanisms in active Brownian particles via deep reinforcement learning

APCTP Workshop for Physics and Machine Learning (Invited talk)

Jeju, Korea Nov. 26. 2021

Methods of estimating entropy production

SEOUL NATIONAL UNIVERSITY STATISTICAL PHYSICS SEMINAR (INVITED TALK)

(Online) Korea

Deep reinforcement learning for feedback-controlled flashing ratchets

KOREAN PHYSICAL SOCIETY FALL MEETING (CONFERENCE, ORAL)

(Online) Korea

Feb. 1, 2021

Nov. 6, 2020

Discovering wiring patterns of neural networks via backboning

NETSCI2020 (CONFERENCE, ORAL)

(Online) Rome, Italy Sep. 22, 2020

Neural estimator for entropy production

KOREAN PHYSICAL SOCIETY SPRING MEETING (CONFERENCE, ORAL)

(Online) Korea

Quantifying Individual Reputation in Large-scale Historical Documents

QUANTIFYING SUCCESS SATELLITE AT NETSCI2019 (CONFERENCE, ORAL)

Burlington, Vermont, USA

May. 27, 2019

Jul. 13, 2020

Teaching Experience

Computational Physics

INVITED TALK

KAIST, Korea Apr. 24 & May. 1, 2023

Physics and AI Winter School

INVITED TALK

(Online) Korea Feb. 24, 2022

General Physics II

TEACHING ASSISTANT

KAIST, Korea 2016 (Fall), 2017 (Spring)

SEPTEMBER 26, 2023

References

Hawoong Jeong

Professor Department of Physics, KAIST Daejeon 34141, Korea

→ hjeong@kaist.edu

Meeyoung Cha

Associate Professor School of Computing, KAIST Daejeon 34141, Korea

Yongjoo Baek

Assistant Professor Department of Physics & Astronomy, SNU Seoul 08826, Korea

y.baek@snu.ac.kr

y.baek@

Junghyo Jo

Assistant Professor Department of Physics Education, SNU Seoul 08826, Korea

☑ jojunghyo@snu.ac.kr